Bowers mss. III, 1868-1972 LMC 1114
Lilly Library
Bowers mss. III
1868-1972
Lilly Library
Bowers, Claude G. (Claude Gernade), 1879-1958
LMC 1114
7 Boxes 6 standard, 1 oversize
1 folio oversize
The Bowers mss. III, 1868-1972, consist of correspondence, speeches, writings, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia relating to Claude Gernade Bowers. The correspondence, dating from 1902-1972, is chiefly between members of the Bowers family, with almost five hundred letters from Sybil (McCaslin) Bowers to Claude Bowers before their marriage. Of particular interest are the letters of the 1930's written by Bowers to his daughter Patricia, giving information about personalities and events in Spain. There are also a number of letters from Holman Hamilton to Patricia Bowers.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Claude Gernade Bowers was born on November 20, 1878, in Westfield, IN, to Lewis Bowers and Juliet Tipton. He spent his childhood in rural Indiana and his adolescence in Indianapolis. After graduating from Indianapolis High School in 1898, Bowers worked a few years for the publisher Bowen-Merrill Company. His journalistic career began in 1901 when Bowers became an editorial writer for the Sentinel. A passionate Democrat, Bowers advocated for progressive reforms in both print and public speeches; he gained a reputation as the "Gatling Gun Orator of the Wabash." A couple of years later in 1903, Bowers moved to Terre Haute, IN, to write for the Gazette and Star and served on the city's Board of Public Works from 1906 to 1911. In 1904 and 1906, he ran as a Democratic candidate for the congressional representative of Terre Haute's district but lost both times to the Republican incumbent. In 1911, Bowers married Sybil McCaslin; the couple had one daughter, Patricia. Bowers moved to Washington, D.C., to work as secretary to John Worth Kern, the U.S. senator from Indiana, from 1911-1917. While in the nation's capital, Bowers wrote political articles for a number of Indiana newspapers and assisted Senator Kern in his efforts to push New Freedom legislation through the Senate. In 1916, Senator Kern lost his bid for reelection, and the following year, Bowers moved back to Indiana, this time settling in Fort Wayne where he was editor of the Journal-Gazette.
In 1923, Bowers moved to New York City and worked as an editorial writer for New York World from 1923-1931 and a political columnist for the New York Journal from 1931-1933. While in New York City, Bowers also wrote speeches for the politicians Al Smith, Robert F. Wagner, and Franklin D. Roosevelt. As a keynote speaker at the 1928 Democratic convention, Bowers notably criticized Presidents Warren G. Harding and Calvin Coolidge, and he campaigned for Franklin D. Roosevelt in the 1932 presidential election. From 1933 to 1939, Bowers served as ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Spain; as an American diplomat to Spain, he worked to improve Spanish-American trade and supported the side of the Spanish Republic in the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939). From 1939 to 1953, Bowers served as a U.S. ambassador to Chile, and during World War II, he persuaded the Chilean government to break ties with the Axis powers. Aside from his career as a newspaperman and diplomat, Bowers succeeded as a historical writer and biographer. Among his notable historical works are Jefferson and Hamilton (1925) and The Tragic Era: The Revolution after Lincoln (1929); he authored biographies of Senator John Kern (1918), Senator Albert J. Beveridge (1932), and Pierre Vergniaud (1950). His autobiography, My Life: The Memoirs of Claude Bowers, was published in 1962. Bowers died in New York City on January 21, 1958, at the age of 79.
Scope and Contents
The Correspondence series contains correspondence with Bowers and his family from 1902 to 1972. Of particular interest are Bowers' letters of the 1930s sent to his daughter, Patricia, that describe personalities and events in Spain during the civil war. Diaries consists of two diaries kept by Sybil McCaslin Bowers from 1933 to 1951. Embassy Materials contains diplomatic lists and other documents related to the U.S. Embassy in Spain and the U.S. Embassy in Chile during Bowers' ambassadorships in those countries. Speeches includes speeches written by Bowers and others. Writings is divided into writings by Bowers on Chile, politics, and his life and writings by other authors. Newspaper Clippings consists of 79 clippings dating from 1905 to 1958. Miscellaneous includes among other items two of Bowers' publishing agreements and three original political cartoons. Photographs contain six albums and several folders of loose photos. Awards and Medals, subdivided accordingly into "Awards" and "Medals," consists of 22 awards and medals Bowers received from 1924 to 1957.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Diaries; III. Embassy Materials; IV. Speeches, V. Writings, VI. Newspaper Clippings; VII. Miscellaneous; VIII. Photographs; IX. Awards and Medals
Indiana--Politics and government; International relations; Journalism; Women; Bowers, Claude G. (Claude Gernade), 1879-1958
- I. CORRESPONDENCE
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Albright, Edward
  Benton, William
  Bernard, Silas G.
  Bowers, Claude Gernade
  Bowers, Sybil McCaslin (Mrs. Claude Gernade Bowers)
  Cermak, Anton Joseph
  Cooper, Zelia Scott
  Crawford, John Lamb
  Errazuriz, Jorge
  Gerdink, Herbert R.
  Greenslet, Ferris
  Grez Geuiguren, Manuel
  Hagey, Frank
  Hamilton, Holman
  Hawes, Harry Barton
  Hopper, Hazel W.
  Howard, Findley Burtch
  Ingle, B. B.
  Joel, Iloe Bowers
  Kahn, Herman
  Knox, Charles Frederick Jr.
  Kober, Samuel
  Lamb, John K.
  Lewis, E.
  McCaslin, Donovan
  McCaslin, Mary (Mrs. Donovan McCaslin)
  Macchi, Francesco
  McDonald, William H.
  Markland, Mary
  Mathews, William
  Navarrete, America Patricia
  Nevins, Allan
  O'Brien, Frank Michael
  O'Hair, Frank T.
  Oliver, Frank
  Ragland, James
  Roberts, Bessie Keeran
  Roosevelt, Anna Eleanor Roosevelt (Mrs. Franklin Delano Roosevelt)
  Shagley, Mary
  Shouse, Jouett
  Skinner, LeRoy J.
  Smith, Fred
  Spencer, John Wesley
  Thornbrough, Gayle
  Tyler, Lyon Gardiner
  Wall, Robert W. Jr.
  Weigel, Gustave
  Zirkle, Mary C.
  - 1902-1903, Feb. (Box 1)
  - 1903, Mar.-Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1903, May-June (Box 1)
  - 1903, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1904, Jan.-Mar. (Box 1)
  - 1904, Apr.-June (Box 1)
  - 1904, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1905, Jan.-Mar. (Box 1)
  - 1905, Sept.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1906-1907, July (Box 1)
  - 1907, Aug.-1908, June (Box 1)
  - 1908, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1909, Jan.-Mar. (Box 1)
  - 1909, Apr.-June (Box 1)
  - 1909, July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1909, Oct.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1910, Jan.-Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1910, May-June (Box 1)
  - 1910, July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1910, Oct.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1911, Jan.-Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1911, May-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914-1929 (Box 2)
  - 1930-1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1951, Aug. (Box 2)
  - 1951, Sept.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1952-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960 (Box 2)
  - 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970-n.d. (Box 2)
- II. DIARIES
  Diaries of Sybil (McCaslin) Bowers. Arranged chronologically.
  - May 1933-23 August 1951 (Box 2)
  - 17 April 1937-9 October 1938 (Box 2)
- III. EMBASSY MATERIALS
  - Embassy in Spain
    - Diplomatic lists (Box 2)
    - Social affairs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Embassy in Chile
    - Diplomatic lists (Box 2)
    - Social affairs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- IV. SPEECHES
  - Bowers (Box 3)
  - Non-Bowers (Box 3)
- V. WRITINGS
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bowers
    - "Chile through Embassy Windows," undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - "The Heritage of Jefferson" and "In defense of politicians", 1943 (Box 3)
    - "My life," undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Columbia University oral history research office - interviews with Claude Bowers, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Non-Bowers
    - Folder 10 (Box 4)
      General
      The Annexation of Texas
      Collection of seven letters exchanged between Spanish Republican leaders in Mexico City
      Hubbard, John Randolph - "How Franco financed his war"
      Iberica for a free Spain
      Inter-American Notes
    - Folder 11 (Box 4)
      Kern family
      Mensaje
      Occidente; La cultura por la cultura
      The Political News
      The Treaty of Washington
      U.S. 71st Congress, 1st session, 1929
- VI. NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS
  - 1905-1958 (Box 4)
- VII. MISCELLANEOUS
  - Menus and invitations (Box 4)
  - Funeral memorabilia (Box 4)
  - Henri Vergniaud materials (Box 4)
  - Publishing agreements (Box 4)
  - Assorted (Box 4)
  - Political cartoons (Ovflat 35)
  - Bronze bust of Claude Bowers (Vault 1)
  - Academic robes (Vault 1)
- VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND ALBUMS
  - Signature album (Box 2)
  - Five albums (Box 6)
  - Loose photographs (Folders 1-4) (Box 7)
  - Loose oversize photographs (Folder 5) (Box 5 (oversize))
- IX. AWARDS AND MEDALS
  - Awards
    - Charter member of Bill and Tom Township Club, 22 October 1930 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Certificate from the Mayor of New York, 1 February 1932 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Law degree from Ogelthorpe University, 29 May 1932 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Certificate from the Liquid Purveyors Association, 1 July 1932 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Honorary diploma from New York Board of Education, 11 July 1932 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Certificate from the National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1937 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Appointment by Calvin Coolidge to the Sesquicentennial Committee, 5 May 1950 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Certificate from the Scouts de la tropa "Alfonso de Ligario", September 1951 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Citation for the biography of Pierre Vergniaud, 8 April 1952 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Honorary degree from the Instituto de Investigaciones Historicas, Santiago, 21 August 1957 (Box 5 (oversize))
  - Medals
    - Democratic Convention medals, 1924-1928 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Thomas Jefferson medal, 5 July 1926 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Medal commemorating the entry of Lafayette ship into service, May 1930 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Republican convention medal, 1932 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Copper plaque from testimonial dinner, 28 February 1933 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Decoration, Santiago, September 1949 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Medal commemorating Gabriel Gonzalez Videla's visit to the U.S., 1950 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Picture presented by Francisco Caballero M., 1950 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - French medal, 8 April 1952 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Columbia University Bicentennial medal, 1954 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Medal of Universitas Catholica Chilensis, 1955 (Box 5 (oversize))
    - Bronze U.S. medal, undated (Box 5 (oversize))